<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: CAT Preparation | Hacker's Diary]]></title>
  <link href="http://karthikselva.github.com/blog/categories/cat-preparation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://karthikselva.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-06T00:13:53+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://karthikselva.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[karthikselva's log]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mathematics - Basic CAT ]]></title>
    <link href="http://karthikselva.github.com/blog/2009/08/09/mathematics-basic-cat/"/>
    <updated>2009-08-09T20:39:51+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://karthikselva.github.com/blog/2009/08/09/mathematics-basic-cat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well as far as mathematics is concerned its more simpler elementary mathematics there.
But time is the only factor which decides the toppers in CAT . hence its so good to have shortcuts for elementary addition , multiplication .Repettative solving of all possible cat questions can only help you in finishing of question in esteemed time .
Try to learn shortcuts of tables.</p>

<pre><code>                                This will help  you must  have a [look at this ](http://listverse.com/2007/09/17/10-easy-arithmetic-tricks/)
</code></pre>

<p>If you have enough time to learn and apply all shortcuts <a href="http://mathforum.org/k12/mathtips/beatcalc.html">then try this </a></p>

<p>Meet you soon on maths !!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[English a basic need for CAT]]></title>
    <link href="http://karthikselva.github.com/blog/2009/08/09/english-a-basic-need-for-cat/"/>
    <updated>2009-08-09T20:28:20+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://karthikselva.github.com/blog/2009/08/09/english-a-basic-need-for-cat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ya english is higly needed for scoring a reasonable mark in CAT . May be easier for who have completed BEC or TOEFL or other standard courses . well then for who start from scratch wihout enough knowledge in english ( like me ) you may do read "The Hindu " .</p>

<p>I know its a tougher job to start with reading even a paragraph at start . Then find the words which are new words Have a mark ther . then proceed reading till para ends. Then come back to first line search in your dictionary the words . ( kind advice is to have a book edition of dictionary rather refering softwares ) . well then read the para again ( with meaning of every words known ) and understand the meaning.</p>

<p>At start most of the words in newspaper may resemble new to you . But they will start reducing if you proceed this till atleast amonth .then move on from a single para to few para 's extra .then increase the number of pages you read per day.</p>

<p>Test how many words you can read at one minute .keep track on this and reduce this for even complicated paragraphs .</p>

<p>Then meet you soon with next excercise !!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
